welcome to the stola the stoah is a
digital campfire where we go here and
dialogue about what matters most at the
night's edge what's happening now
[Music]
let's do some check-ins yeah there's
like a nervous energy and its associated
with some like performance quality
performative quality like I kind of want
to perform right now that's associated
with a lightness and I feel a little
jovial because I got a little bit of
Ali's energy coming in chatting
beforehand so welcome to the stoah i am
peter limber the stewart of the stoah
and the stoah is the place for us to
cohere and dialogue about what matters
most have a nice edge this moment and
today we have my buddy
Alexander miner from rebel wisdom and
yeah so I'm I was the community manager
tribalism until the damon pulled me away
into this project and I'm a
correspondent for them in Toronto and I
really like what they're doing I think
they are the journalists that we need
now in this liminal space or potentially
liminal war because they have not only
the mind but the heart to sort of
navigate this space and Sally wrote this
like really really awesome article I
make sure I get the name right
traversing the underworld where he talks
about the mythology that's at play and
being sort of put online in this liminal
space and he has a lot of great framing
there that's helping me understand
what's happening with with this
so-called liminal war that I think is
coming online so I'm really excited to
have him here today that to chat about
it something said how today's gonna work
Ally's gonna share his thoughts about
the article maybe share the premises
we'll have maybe a back and forth chat
warm up the room and then if you have a
question just put in the chat box and
then meet yourself when I want to call
your name or if you want me to read on
your path just let me know that when in
the chat box as well that being said
Ally I think I have to let you unmute
yourself now yeah handing over to you
yeah there we go how can I make myself
great thank you for the intro Peter and
hi everybody thanks for coming it's
really nice to see actually quite a few
familiar faces and familiar names in all
places as well so yeah that's that's
really nice yeah it actually might be
useful just to see a show of hands who
either had a chance to read the article
or see the film that we put out at the
same time
cool okay I'll do a brief brief summary
in any case because I think well we'll
use that as a kind of springboard and
then then just have an open conversation
so the suppose that the reason for the
article and the film was this curiosity
around its phrase that kept coming up
and that I think a lot of people feel
which is this idea of being between what
zaxxon calls being between two worlds or
being in the liminal and I've used this
metaphor a few times of the liminal
myself and also I really loved the
etymology of it where the word comes
from because it uh come well close to my
heart in some ways because Lehman in
Latin is threshold it's kind of the edge
of things and where I grew up actually
in in Germany was very close to you know
a five minute walk from the Lehman that
which was the wall that divided the
Roman Empire from the Germanic tribes
and so I always had that in my head you
know and you could go and walk the wall
and this is very kind of visceral
visible touchable boundary that was a
boundary between two completely
different worlds and when you step
through the threshold that's actually
you know that word threshold comes from
our word for doorway so if the Old
English for doorway and that's kind of
what we've done we've stepped through
our doorways into our homes into this
completely other world and like it often
is in mythology the liminal
can look very much like the world you've
come from but be completely different
and the rules that used to apply no
longer apply
and so that's an experience that I
certainly have in this during this
crisis and I'm you know actually from
conversations with Peter this idea of
the liminal war also really you know
which was an idea I heard from Peter
like that really kind of got me thinking
as well you know this is a it's not only
a space we're in but it's a space where
we're really in some way potentially
gonna be battling for the for the kind
of people we're gonna be in the kind of
society and the kind of culture we're
gonna have forgetting about where we
might go for a moment because that's
really difficult to tell in the liminal
you know the the kind of idea of
direction becomes very different when
you're in what in in myth is very often
an underworld so that's why the the
title was called Traverse in the
underworld because one of the most
potent symbols of the liminal is the
underworld is this place where I'm very
often a hero or in the case of Demeter
and Persephone a goddess might have to
travel down into the underworld to
rescue someone or to go through some
kind of front deep transformation and
come out and as one of the people I
interviewed for the article said
Charlotte McCann she was like it's
really easy to get into the underworld
because all you have to do is die and we
were you know in mythic terms you could
say that we've all been in some way
transported into an underworld or in
Celtic mythology was often an Otherworld
that's kind of right beside or between
our world and once were in that while it
might be easy to get in there and you
can almost fall in there accidentally as
does happen in some stories it's really
difficult to get out and it requires
certain qualities of a character in a
story or a myth that's
that include resilience perseverance
kind of often a good heart is a big part
of it just a kind of sense of integrity
and clear and clean purpose and so that
really calls to me because I think you
know big part of what we've been
exploring with rebel wisdom is what are
the practices and what are the ways of
being that will help us to be the kind
of people we might need to be to thrive
in the environment we're in and the kind
of people that we might have been
trained to be might not be fit for
purpose and we might be cold now into
another very mythic term which is
initiation to initiate into a new way of
being and so that's that's a lot of the
themes I was exploring the article yeah
but I also spoke to a kind of a hero of
mine
Steven Jenkinson who is Canadian I think
he's been on this I think he's been on
the stove if I'm correct yeah or
certainly Peter spoke to him earlier
yeah interviewed him yeah interviewed
him yeah so yeah and hid you know he is
holding some very deep wisdom in my view
and he was a palliative care counsellor
for many years sat with many thousand
people as they died and then wrote a
book called die wise it was featured in
a great documentary called grief Walker
which was on a Canadian TV station and
his what I really found fascinating
about his perspective is how he talks
about our cultures not only our
inability to have a healthy relationship
with death and what that actually means
I wanted me to die well but also our
inability to talk about endings I think
that's a really key point I want to pull
out in this intro as well it's like
because that was kind of a real shift
for me because I'm the product of my own
culture and that you know we talked
about transition or someone passed on or
transition or like a phase shift or all
these different things and we don't ever
really talk about endings and in order
to allow something to die like a culture
that wasn't working and various systems
that were
are too fragile to ever be sustained we
also have to talk about endings and
that's really key and yeah so him
charlotte de kan is featured in the
article she talks about as well another
key point which is that there is very
famously the hero's journey in mythology
so this process where for example you
know Frodo is really comfortable in the
state disco and the Shire in a really
safe place and then he has a call to
adventure and Gandalf who tells him to
to come on this kind of grand adventure
to dispose of this ring and then he
steps past his comfort zone and then
there's a process of passing the first
threshold which actually in the film
Lord of the Rings
is a really visceral moment it's there's
a bit where Sam and Frodo are walking
and Sam suddenly stops and he says if I
take one more step it'll be the furthest
away from home I've ever been I'm that's
passing the first threshold so he takes
that step obviously and then once they
do that they go through various
challenges and their characteristic the
result is tested their friendship is
tested and that is the very often the
hero's journey there is a process of
going into the cave going to the
underworld slaying the dragon coming
back to the community with the gold and
this process in in myth and in the study
of myth there's something called the
monomyth the idea that we actually are
only really telling one story and that
story of an individual's process from
going from immaturity to maturity from
less awareness to more awareness from a
small view of just safe in your comfort
zone to a more expansive world centric
view where you have a role in the
community and you have a purpose in the
world so what was interesting talking to
Charlotte Charlotte diccon was actually
pointed out that there's a very there's
a very different female initiation
journey as well which is kind of the
inverse of that where you start from
being a princess and you start in a kind
of and in the place where you're
elevated and then you go in a process
where you are pulled down
is kind of stripping away of all the
finery and all the things that weren't
really you and then you're down in the
in the ashes in doing what she calls
kitchen work there's this process of
being humbled and going down back into
the earth and back into a deeper deeper
connection and yet it requires of course
all of those same qualities of resolve
determination a true heart compassion
care for others and in that process of
going down rather than going outwards
there's a transformation and so my
feeling right now is that what we're
going through doesn't feel to me like a
male initiatory journey as much as I
love that process and in fact Peters
been in our men's weekend and we use the
hero's journey as like that the way to
guide the whole process
I in some ways live my life with a deep
connection to that that initiatory
journey and so very different yeah that
is that's a really good point from
Jordan that is a lot like Pan's
Labyrinth actually so yeah so that
process of coming down rather than going
out in this grand adventure like I don't
feel like and this was a thought I had
kind of before writing the article it's
like I really don't feel like I'm being
called into a grand adventure I feel
like I'm being called to something else
like where am I gonna go I don't know
it's like I've been on like a grand
adventure in some ways and I've been
trying to achieve and and doing stuff
and like that's great there something
wrong with that that's that's one half
of the process I think um or of a
potential process but right now it feels
very much more like what what Charlotte
McCann is pointing out of this going
down into the darkness into the the
humor so she called it humorous meaning
the earth the ground which is actually
where we get the word humility from and
potentially the word human interestingly
a little bit more of a roundabout
etymology to it but all these lovely
signs and nods in our language I really
love to follow so that's really the
process I think that's kind of like the
general gist of what the film and the
article are about and some of the themes
I think are really alive right now so I
think I'll leave it there and yeah so
so I mean so much to chat about
so if I'll warm up ally in the room with
some questions and we'll just maybe jam
back and forth if you have any questions
write it down the chat box we'll get to
that in a moment so let's see which we
begin hmm there's a dangerous question I
want to begin with in a safe question so
my sense is were the safe question first
so uh John Vicki was on the stove and
then he said something that came out
which is so almost like a rally cry that
I'm putting the stove behind is it steal
the culture we got to steal the culture
right and if you're a good thief you
don't announce your coming you just take
and when you kind of look at culture the
game a culture if you want to use that
terminology
it's like culture and cultural artifacts
or in service of the ego right where
true culture seems to be designed to
keep the ego in check all right and then
what what's happening notice with the
stole is like a community is is forming
community Oz culture is happening I like
like my boy Tyson is in the room right
now and he's doing this every Saturday
he's doing freestyling through a
pandemic and so we're just doing like
freestyle rap and but with this in
service of speaking truth of what
speaking of now sourcing through the
Damon and I don't freestyle right and I
was freestyling fat first time and the
was coming out I don't know it was
good or not but then just the love there
and getting that collective flow right
and so the egos being kept and checked
there we're feeling communitas but we're
doing culture right and so like I just I
guess I don't have a question but what
do you think about that stealing the
culture and having that transition from
being service to the ego and keeping it
in the ego in check yeah that's a good
question or topic the what springs to
mind is is there's a wonderful book
called the seven basic plots by
christopher Booker which is really long
so 1200 pages long but it's really
really worth reading and he covers he
took him 20 years to write it I think he
includes something like six or seven
hundred or more
stories from ER